A Guide to the Governor John Tyler Executive Papers, 1808-1811
Library of Virginia
Additional significant correspondence includes the following: David S. Garland resigning as Register of the Land Office (1808 Dec. 13); David Sheffey, Chairman of the Armory Committee, re. the manner in which the public armory has been conducted (1808 Dec. 22); Thomas Newton re. fortifications for the defense of Norfolk & Portsmouth (1808 Dec. 26); Alexander Quarrier re. his account for repairs on the Public Square (1808 Dec. 27); Alexander Quarrier re. repairs done on the Public Square by order of Gov. Cabell (1809 Jan. 12); John Preston resigning as major general of the 3rd Division of the Militia (1809 Jan. 17); Henry Blow, William Blow, & Samuel Blunt, Trustees of the Nottoway Tribe of Indians, re. their lands on the north side of the Nottoway River (1809 Feb. 17 & 1809 May 11); Alexander Stuart resigning as a member of the Privy Council (1809 March 18); Maurice Rogers, U.S. Consul at St. Jago de Cuba, encl. the proclamation of Governor Sebastian Kindelan ordering the French inhabitants to quit the island (1809 April 28); John Guerrant, Jr., resigning from the Council of State (1809 May 27); D. J. Burr, Agent of the Penitentiary encl. an invoice of shoes made under the supervision of Martin Mims as Keeper (1809 May 26); William Vaughan, Magistrate in Norfolk, re. the arrival of French inhabitants driven from Cuba with their slaves (1809 June 2); Edward Carrington re. the powder magazine in Richmond (1809 June 3); Henry Deringer, Philadelphia, offering to contract with the Commonwealth to manufacture two hundred rifles annually (1809 June 12); Peter Crutchfield, Commandant of the Public Guard, re. stationary and an account from Samuel Shepard (1809 June 16); John E. Holt, Mayor of Norfolk, re. ships from Cuba with French inhabitants & their slaves (1809 June 17); John Strode encl. an estimate of the expense of a forge with one hammer (1809 Dec. 30); Henry Deringer, Philadelphia, re. an offer to contract with Virginia to manufacture five hundred rifles annually (1810 Jan. 17); John Preston, Treasurer, requesting permission to remove the Treasury Office into a room of the third story of the Capitol (1810 Feb. 10); Benjamin Duval re. fireplaces in the offices of the General Court & Auditor (includes drawings) (1810 March 8); Richard Byrd re. a feared insurrection in Smithfield (1810 May 30); L.A. Pauly encl. a sketch of the administration of the Royal Manufactory of Arms of Charleville (1810 May 1 & 31; 1810 June 6, 12, 19, & 26); John M. Carter re. the completion of the sword for Lt. O'Bannon (1810 July 6); Thomas Underwood encl. an estimate of the expense of digging a canal for the conveyance of produce to the Public Warehouse in Richmond (1810 July 17); James Greenhow re. the sewer at the Penitentiary (1810 July 12); William W. Hening resigning from the Council of State in order to accept an appointment as clerk of the Superior Court of Chancery (1810 Aug. 1); William W. Hening re. the poor condition of the office of the Superior Court of Chancery in the Capitol (1810 Aug. 2); and Jared Brooks encl. a map of the falls of the Ohio with explanatory notes (enclosures not included) (1810 Dec. 10).
Other noteworthy items include: bonds of Edward C. Davis as Register of the Land Office (1808 Dec. 13 & 1810 Feb. 20); the proposal by Samuel Pleasants, Jr., to supply the Commonwealth with 1500 copies of "Steuben's Regulations for the Order & Discipline of the Troops of the U.S." (1809 Jan. 16); a return of arms in the Arsenal of the Capitol by Alexander Quarrier (1809 Jan. 27); a bond of John Staples as Superintendent of the Manufactory of Arms (1809 Feb. 18); a report of all the arms that have been proved & examined in the Capitol & Armory by George Charter, Robert Stewart, & Nevin Karins (1809 Feb. 27; 1809 April 5; & 1809 May 5); a report of the Congressional Committee re. the memorial of William Lambert to establish the first meridian for the United States at the permanent seat of government (1809 March 9 & 1810 March 9); bonds of James Bootwright to furnish rations for the Penitentiary (1809 April 17 & 1810 March 21); proclamations from Governor Tyler regarding rewards for the capture of convicts (1809 May 1; 1809 Aug. 29; 1809 Sept. 25; & 1810 Jan. 25); a report by George Charter & Robert Stewart of all the old arms found in the arsenals of the Capitol & Armory (1809 May 27); a resolution from Samuel A. Otis, Secretary of the U.S. Senate, re. the appointment of a committee to enquire into the expediency of making a provision by law for remitting the penalties incurred by the violations of the act prohibiting the importation of slaves as far as it relates to the slaves brought by the French inhabitants expelled from Cuba (1809 June 12); a decree of the Superior Court of Chancery in the case of Philip Turpin against the Attorney General regarding the value of his two acres of land on Shockoe Hill conveyed on 9 April 1788 (1809 June 23); the commission of James Semple as judge of the General Court (1809 June 24); the bond of Robert Stewart for the repair of public arms (1809 July 6); a proclamation of Governor Tyler ordering that the next courts for Culpeper County be held at the new courthouse (1809 July 24); proceedings of the Quarterly Meeting of the Board of Visitors at the Penitentiary (1809 July 26 & 1810 Dec. 20); a table showing the number of prisoners convicted from each District, their place of nativity, years sentenced, & crime (1809 Dec. 1); an inventory of materials & component parts of arms on hand at the Armory (1809 Dec. 1); a bond of William Byrd to transport two condemned slaves under sentence of death out of the United States (1809 Dec. 7); bonds of Samuel Pleasants as Public Printer (1809 Dec. 15 & 1811 Jan. 11); bonds of Charles Blagrove as Register of the Land Office (1810 Jan. 2 & 1811 Jan. 8); a bond of John Staples as Superintendent of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms (1810 Feb. 17); a list of prisoners in the Penitentiary on 1 July 1810 along with their crimes, dated received, & term of confinement (1810 July 1); a proclamation by Lt. Gov. George William Smith re. a reward for the apprehension of Thomas Harris (1810 July 11); a bond of Mann S. Valentine as agent to the Commonwealth to make sale of certain articles manufactured at the Penitentiary (1810 Oct. 7); proceedings of the Monthly Board of Visitors from Sept. to Nov. 1810 (1810 Nov. 3); and a resolution of the Maryland General Assembly to appoint commissioners to meet with commissioners of Virginia in order to settle & adjust the western boundary of the state (1810 Dec. 7).
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically by date of document with undated items arranged to the rear.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Flournoy, H. W., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, January 1, 1808-December 31, 1835, VOL. X, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1892.
Separated Material
Oversized materials have been separated into Oversized (Clamshell Box) and Oversized (Newspaper Box).
Contents List
- John Tyler Executive Papers
- 1808
  - December (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1809
  - January
    - 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - February
    - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 16-28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - March
    - 2-15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - April
    - 1-10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 11-20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 22-30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - May
    - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - June
    - 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 11-20 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 21-30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - July
    - 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 11-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 21-31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - August
    - 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 11-19 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 21-31 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - September
    - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - October
    - 2-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - November
    - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 16-29 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - December
    - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 18-30 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 1810
  - January
    - 1-9 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 11-20 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 22-31 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - February
    - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 16-28 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - March
    - 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 12-20 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 21-31 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - April
    - 1-14 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - May
    - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - June
    - 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 11-20 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 21-30 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - July
    - 1-10 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 11-20 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 21-31 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - August
    - 1-7 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 8-20 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 21-30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - September
    - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 17-28 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - October
    - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - November
    - 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 11-20 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 21-30 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - December
    - 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 11-20 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 21-31 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
- 1811
  - January
    - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Oversized (Clamshell Box)
  - 1808
    - Dec. 19 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Dec. 21 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1809
    - Jan. [N.D.] (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Feb. 6 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - March 30 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - May 5 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - May 29 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - May 31 (Box 7, Folder 7a)
    - June 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - June 23 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - June 26 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - July 7 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - July 28 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Oct. 27 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Nov. 29 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Dec. 25 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - 1810
    - Jan. 11 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Feb. 20 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - April 9 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - June 14 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - June 21 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - June 22 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - June 22 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Aug. 4 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Aug. 7 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Aug. 27 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Nov. 1 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Nov. [N.D.] (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Dec. 4 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Oversized (Newspaper Box)
  - 1809
    - Feb. 27 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - April 5 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - April 28 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - May 5 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - May 27 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - June 10 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Aug. 17 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Oct. 20 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Dec. 1 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Dec. 7 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 1810
    - June 18 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - July 18 (Box 8, Folder 12)